<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The anatomy of Dr. Gauden's idolized non-sence and blasphemy, in his pretended Analysis, or setting forth the true sense of the covenant that is to say, of that sacred covenant taken by the Parliament, the commissioners of Scotland, and the assembly, September 11. 1643.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E765_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207156</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895228</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895228</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152539</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75313)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152539)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2301:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The anatomy of Dr. Gauden's idolized non-sence and blasphemy, in his pretended Analysis, or setting forth the true sense of the covenant that is to say, of that sacred covenant taken by the Parliament, the commissioners of Scotland, and the assembly, September 11. 1643.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year M DC LX. [1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 19".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gauden, John, 1605-1662. --  Analysis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152539:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANATOMY OF D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s Idolized <hi>Non-ſence</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> IN HIS Pretended <hi>Analyſis,</hi> or <hi>ſetting forth</hi> the true Senſe OF THE COVENANT; That is to ſay, Of that <hi>SACRED COVENANT</hi> taken by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the <hi>Aſſembly, September</hi> 11. 1643.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cyprian ad Cornelium.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Atque haec Frater, vere eſt dementia, non cogitare, nec ſcire, quod mendacia non diu fallant.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152539:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152539:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE ANATOMY OF D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Gauden</hi>'s idolized <hi>Non-ſence</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> IN His pretended <hi>Analyſis</hi> of the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the the better underſtanding of this buſineſs, the Readers both of that Book and this, muſt know, That the late <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> (I mean, both the honourable Houſes) drew up, took, and ordered others to take, two ſeveral <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> in one year. The firſt was taken in or about the beginning of <hi>June</hi> 1643. entituled,
<note place="margin">See more of this neer the end of this Book.</note> 
               <hi>The Vow and Covenant appointed by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by every man, in the Cities of</hi> London, Weſtminſter, <hi>and the Suburbs and Liberties thereof, and throughout the whole Kingdom.</hi> The other was that <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> which the ſame <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of the Kingdom and Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines,</hi> took at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the 11 day of <hi>September,</hi> in the ſame year, and appointed it to be taken by both Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Now, you are to take notice, that it is onely the <hi>laſt</hi> (the far better of the two) which this affected Maſter of Words, (and of little elſe, for ought appears by this and ſundry other things by him written
<note n="†" place="margin">Witneſs his <hi>tears, ſighs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Church of</hi> England. His <hi>Sermon</hi> at <hi>Pauls,</hi> as it was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>) hath <hi>oppoſed,</hi> inſtead of <hi>explaining;</hi> and, againſt which, he hath lately thrown out among his deluded Admirers, a new flatulent Piece (as <hi>Jupiter</hi> did his Log among the Frogs) which he calleth, <hi>Analyſis,</hi> or, <hi>The looſing of St.</hi> Peters <hi>bands, ſetting forth the true ſenſe</hi> (if you will believe him) <hi>and ſolution</hi> (that is, the <hi>diſſolution,</hi> if he can effect it) <hi>of the Covenant, ſo far as it relates to the Government of the Church by Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy.</hi> To which Title of his, (as an inlet to his Diſcourſe, as well as warrantie for the <hi>Title</hi>) he hath ſubjoyned part of <hi>Acts</hi> 16.26. <hi>The
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152539:3"/>foundations of the priſon were ſhaken, the doors opened, and every ones bands were looſed.</hi> Thus he rehearſeth that Text.</p>
            <p>Before I fall to unripping of that <hi>Paſquil it ſelf,</hi> I muſt a little conſider the <hi>Title</hi> of it, in which he preſenteth us with a piece of his <hi>Non-ſenſe;</hi> if not <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> to boot. <hi>Non ſenſe,</hi> firſt: For, what <hi>Oedipus</hi> can unriddle thoſe firſt words in it, (<hi>The looſing of St.</hi> Peter<hi>'s bands)</hi> ſo as (according to his undertaking) to make <hi>ſenſe</hi> of them? Was St. <hi>Peter</hi> bound in this <hi>Covenant?</hi> Or: did he impoſe it upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? If neither, why doth this Wordy Doctor call his Book, <hi>The looſing of St.</hi> Peter<hi>'s bands?</hi> If this be not his meaning, what ſenſe can there be of that his vapouring flouriſh?</p>
            <p>And why St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s bands? Oh, he hath a Text for it, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.26. as ye ſaw but now. But, in alledging it, he will rather pare off part of Gods own words, (which run thus, <hi>The foundations of the priſon were ſhaken, and immediately all the doors were opened,</hi> &amp;c.) than not carry on his own affected Cadencies in his ſtile. But this is but one of his Peccadillo's.</p>
            <p>Now, what intendeth he, by this <hi>looſing</hi> of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>bands;</hi> and by that, in <hi>Acts</hi> 16.26? He tells you: <hi>The ſetting forth the true ſenſe and ſolution of the Covenant,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>John Gauden,</hi> D. D. Very good. It is then <hi>John Gauden</hi> that hath <hi>looſed St.</hi> Peter's <hi>bands,</hi> that hath <hi>ſhaken the foundations of the priſon, opened all the doors, and looſed every ones bands</hi> that were in it. If this be not <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> (as he applies it) then, O moſt glorious <hi>John!</hi> Why do not his zealous Adorers ſay of him, as ſometimes the <hi>Barbarians</hi> of <hi>Paul,</hi> That <hi>he is a God?</hi> Why ſend they not for one of the Prieſts of <hi>Jupiter</hi> (I will not ſay, ſome old, high <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copalian</hi>) to <hi>bring Oxen and Garlands, to ſacrifice unto him, with the people?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How beit, <hi>dic ſodes,</hi> Doctor. Was it St. <hi>Peter</hi> indeed, that was in Priſon? Were they <hi>his bands</hi> that you have <hi>looſed?</hi> I verily were they, by your telling. And therefore, though the Text be far from ſaying any ſuch matter, yet if Doctor <hi>John Gauden</hi> ſay it, it muſt be believed without gain-ſaying, though he prove it not. Nevertheleſs, if we may be ſo bold, as to conſult the verſe next going before, we might (if we durſt) tell him,
<note place="margin">Act. 16.25.</note> that we find onely <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas;</hi> but no St. <hi>Peter</hi> there: unleſs he will ſay (which he may as well ſay, as what he doth; for, it is not his manner to prove ought) that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> is Greek for St. <hi>Peter;</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> is Engliſh for <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas;</hi> and ſo, they are all one.</p>
            <p>But perhaps St. <hi>Peter</hi> (in this mans intention) denotes his Succeſſors at <hi>Rome;</hi> with whom this charitable Doctor profeſſeth (elſewhere
<note n="*" place="margin">In his <hi>tears, ſighs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Church of</hi> England. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ag. 314.</note>) a deſire to hold not onely <hi>all inward, but all actual Communion in all Doctrines and Duties of Faith and Worſhip agreeable to the Word of God,</hi> (as if that Romiſh Crew performed any ſuch Duties, without ſo much
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152539:3"/>mixture of will-worſhip and ſuperſtition, as hath not, from the ſame Word of God, procured a ſtrait charge to all Gods people, to <hi>come out of her,</hi> not ſo much in regard of place, as <hi>Communion,</hi> which is doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as a <hi>partaking of her ſins.</hi>) And, if this be his meaning,
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.4.</note> his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity hath ſo far tranſported him, as to looſen what God hath laid on thoſe pretended Succeſſors, and all their <hi>Locuſts;</hi> by upholding <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with <hi>Popery,</hi> which the <hi>Covenaut</hi> engageth all to <hi>extirpate.</hi> If this be his meaning, let him ſpeak out.</p>
            <p>If he mean otherwiſe, he is groſly miſtaken. Indeed, we find St. <hi>Peter</hi> to be caſt into <hi>Priſon</hi> at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> by <hi>Herod,</hi> where he had <hi>chains put upon his hands,</hi> Act. 12. which, by means of the inceſſant <hi>prayers of the Church to God for him,</hi> an <hi>Angel</hi> went and <hi>unlooſed;</hi> open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the priſon doors, and ſo brought him out. But, good Sir, were you that <hi>Angel?</hi> If ſo, let your <hi>Title</hi> ſtand. I will have no further difference with you about it.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> whoſe <hi>impriſonment</hi> is mentioned in your al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Text, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. were impriſoned at <hi>Philippi,</hi> far diſtant from St. <hi>Peters</hi> priſon. And even there, we read of no <hi>bands</hi> upon them, but onely that their <hi>feet were made faſt in the ſtocks.</hi> And, for ought appears, they were not out of the ſtocks, when <hi>the bands of every one</hi> elſe were <hi>looſed:</hi> but they continued therein, till the <hi>Jaylor</hi> himſelf came in, and took them thence. But, be that ſo, or ſo; we will not contend about it.</p>
            <p>Whoſe <hi>bands</hi> then were <hi>looſed?</hi> The bands of the <hi>Jayl birds,</hi> who had been caſt in before: namely, <hi>Thieves,</hi> and perhaps <hi>Murderers,</hi> and other <hi>Rogues</hi> and <hi>Malefactors:</hi> for they are the uſual Gueſts in ſuch places. Now, if any ſuch have taken <hi>the Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> and are thereupon troubled in Conſcience, ſo as not to dare to ſet up the old <hi>Hierarchy</hi> again, with ſome ſmall refining, let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to Dr. <hi>John</hi> to <hi>looſe</hi> them of that <hi>band;</hi> and he will do it. But, for the greater encouragement of ſuch men and others that are for that Lordly Epiſcopacy, and would gladly read his Book, to be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Conſcience therein, I could wiſh the <hi>Title</hi> might be altered, and put into the words of <hi>Martin Mar-prelate,</hi> in anſwer to Dr. <hi>J. Bridges</hi> that had pleaded for ſuch Biſhops and their Trinkets; (onely change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Name) that the <hi>Title</hi> of the Book might run thus:
<q>O read Dr. <hi>John Gauden,</hi> for it is a worthy Work.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Which, how <hi>worthy</hi> it is, we ſhall now further enquire, by looking into the Book it ſelf. In proſecution whereof, I ſhall induſtriouſly avoid the waſte of ſo much time, and paper, as would be taken only up in purſuing all his out-leaps and extravagancies; and uſe all poſſible
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152539:4"/>brevity in opening ſome of the principal onely, for the undeceiving of ſuch as dote upon this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Acts 8.10.</note> or <hi>great one,</hi> as if he were <hi>the great power of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The main ſcope of my preſent endeavour is this: namely, to make it manifeſt, that this Doctor, under pretence of <hi>giving that ſober ſenſe of the Covenant, whereof he believeth it to be capable before God, before all good Chriſtians, and in a mans own well-informed Conſcience,</hi> (which he promiſeth, pag. 3, 4. and to do it with <hi>freedom from paſſion and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice</hi> (pag. 5.) he directly laboureth to decry, vilifie, and blaſpheme the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf, and to make it odious, as that which was ſinfully taken at firſt, and of neceſſity to be caſt off, and abhorred by all that have entred into it. For more diſtinct proceeding therein, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make out theſe four Propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That he himſelf doth admit the Covenant, to be, in ſome ſenſe, lawful and good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That, therein, all ſober Chriſtians, who underſtand them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, agree with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That all this notwithſtanding, he endeavours to vilifie, make odious, and to deſtroy the Covenant it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That, maugre all his calumnies, and malicious aſperſions, the Covenant, (even as to the point of extirpating that hierarchical Prelacy lately laid aſide,) is to be conſtantly and conſcienciouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and kept, in the right ſenſe thereof, by all that have taken it, as they will avoid destruction here, and damnation hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>I. PROPOSITION. <hi>That the Doctor himſelf doth admit the Covenant to be, in ſome ſenſe, lawful and good.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. HIs own words before alledged (where he ſaith he <hi>hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to give that ſober ſenſe of the Covenant, whereof he believeth it to be only capable before God, before all good Chriſtians, and in a mans own well-informed Conſcience</hi>) is evidence enough (againſt him, at leaſt,) <hi>that the Covenant is lawful and good.</hi> How elſe could he give a <hi>ſober ſenſe</hi> of it, which he believes would hold water, <hi>before God, all good men, and a well informed Conſcience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. He tells us (pag. 14.) <hi>that he will look upon the Covenant (with the beſt aſpect, conſidered in Conſcience) in the ſofteſt ſenſe that can be made of it;</hi> namely, <hi>as a voluntary Vow, or Religious Bond, by ſome ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneouſly taken,</hi> in order to declare their <hi>ſenſe of duty to God, the King,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152539:4"/>the Church, their Country, and the reformed Religion, to make themſelves more ſtrictly ſenſible of the ſacred and civil obligations reſpectively due to them, that ſo they might be more ready to diſcharge them in their places and callings,</hi> &amp;c.— (And is not this <hi>lawful,</hi> and <hi>good?</hi>) He after addeth, that <hi>he believeth that very few took it in any ſenſe, againſt Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, Reformed, and Regular Epiſcopacy, ſo reduced to an efficacious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with Presbytery, as the moſt reverend Primate of</hi> Armagh <hi>propoſed in his Reduction of Epiſcopacy.</hi> Now, if ſuch a <hi>Reduction</hi> be neceſſary, the <hi>Covenant</hi> in this ſenſe cannot be <hi>unlawful,</hi> but <hi>good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In pag. the 20. he ſaith, <hi>The moſt ſtrict and ſevere Covenanter can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be ſatisfied and abſolved in point of Conſcience, if firſt he hath and ſtill doth, in his place and calling, ſeaſonably adviſe, humbly petition, and lawfully endeavour to reform what is truely amiſs in the Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Biſhops. Secondly, If he uſe the like means to reſtore and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what he finds good and uſeful in Epiſcopacy.</hi> — They then that do not thus, cannot be <hi>ſatisfied or abſolved in point of Conſcience:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to do this, by vertue of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> is <hi>lawful and good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In his voluminous Book of <hi>Tears and Sighs,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 448. he reckons up ſundry <hi>evils, defects and dangers incident to Epiſcopacy,</hi> as namely, <hi>pride, ambition, ſecular height, and idle pomp, a ſupercilious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciency and Lordly Tyrannizing over other Miniſters, and the flocks of Chriſt under their inſpection; arrogating a power to do all things imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and alone, without any regard either to that charitable ſatisfaction which was antiently given to Chriſtian people; or, to that fraternal Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and concurrence which might and ought in reaſon to be had, from learned and grave Presbyters,</hi> &amp;c.— Is not all this enough to prove from his own Pen, That ſuch a <hi>Covenant, for extirpating ſuch an Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, is lawfully and good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed, he would (in the ſame breath) fain extenuate this his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripping of the late Hierarchy, by ſaying, <hi>that this ariſeth not from the function or imployment, but from the perſons of Biſhops,</hi> (which he brings in, by a <hi>parentheſis:</hi>) but, when he had undertaken to enumerate the evils, defects and dangers <hi>incident to Epiſcopacy</hi> it ſelf, of late in uſe, How can theſe be ſeparated from that <hi>Function?</hi> And if they ariſe <hi>from the perſons of Biſhops;</hi> do they not ariſe from the <hi>imployment</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy?</hi> for, how elſe could they be <hi>incident to Epiſcopacy?</hi> That parentheſis then, is but a piece of contradictory non-ſenſe, which can no way infringe the inference I have here made of it, to confirm, from the Author himſelf, the firſt point here undertaken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152539:5"/>
               <head>II. PROPSITION. <hi>Herein all ſober Chriſtians who understand themſelves, agree with him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is pleaſed indeed, (pag. 6.) from Sir <hi>L.B.</hi> (at whoſe <hi>motion</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 3.</note> he wrote and publiſhed that pamphlet) to ſay, that Sir <hi>L. B.</hi> (a fit Patron for ſuch a Proctor) told him, <hi>that many ſober and honeſt men, are by their once taking the Covenant, ſo ſcared from all complyings with any Church-government, under any name of Biſhops, or notion of Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, never ſo reformed and regulated; that they fear, by looking back to the Primitive; Catholique, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Government of this, and all other antient Churches, to be turned into pillars of Apoſtacy, as Lots wife was, into a pillar of Salt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Knight told him ſo, in theſe words, we muſt needs admire the <hi>metamorphoſis</hi> of a <hi>Cutler</hi> turned Knight, that hath arrived already at ſuch <hi>heards of good words, and flocks of figures:</hi> and, that he, who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore took the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and pretended to be a zealous propugner of it, and of all that had taken it, ſhould now, (in hope to get into ſome place to help maintain his <hi>Knighthood</hi>) leave all thoſe of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer party, and run over to ſuch a flaſhy Advocate for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and a mortal enemy to all <hi>Covenanters,</hi> to aſſoyle the doubts of <hi>ſober honeſt men</hi> that had entred into that Covenant.</p>
               <p>But, if that Knight did ſo inform him, it is be doubted, whether he did it, for want of ignorance, or of <hi>ſtedfaſtneſs in that Covenant</hi> of God, and out of a deſire of procuring (by that his ſtory to the Doctor, and his <hi>motion</hi> for his <hi>reſolution</hi> of this buſineſs, <hi>in point of Conſcience</hi>) ſome plauſible Apology for his own intended <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> However he did it, let that K. take this to him as the forerunner of that reward which he muſt exſpect from that God whoſe Covenant he hath thus occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to be deſpiſed, That all the reproaches and blaſphemies that are or ſhall be belched out againſt the Covenant, (occaſioned by reading that ſcurrilous Satyre of Dr. <hi>John Gauden</hi>) will one day be put to the account of Sir <hi>L. B.</hi> as the principal occaſion of it, and inſtigator to it; if God give him not timely repentance, and ſtop the current of thoſe railing <hi>Shimei's,</hi> who are glad of this opportunity to ſet <hi>their mouths againſt heaven,</hi> and to let <hi>their tongues walk through the earth</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Pſa 73.9.</note>.</p>
               <p>But, to leave this digreſſion. I come to make good the ſecond point; which I enlarge thus; <hi>That the admitting of ſome Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, under the name of Biſhops, reformed and regulated according to the Primitive Catholicue and Apoſtolique Inſtitution, for the Government of this Church, is not againſt, but very conſiſtent with, and agreeable to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152539:5"/>late Solemn League and Covenant, and the true intention of it, allowable by God and all good men that rightly underſtand themſelves and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. And,</hi> thus far, <hi>they concur with the Doctor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To make this out briefly, take notice</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Covenant, Art.</hi> 2. as to this point, runs thus: <hi>That we ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtantly (through the grace of God) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the extirpation of Popery and Prelacy (that is, Church government by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellors and Commiſſaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Archdeacons and all other Eccleſiaſtical Officers depending on that Hierarchy.) Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſm, Prophaneſs, and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound Doctrine and the power of godlineſs; leſt we partake in other mens ſins, and thereby be in danger to receive of their plagues; and, that the Lord may be one, and his name one in the three Kingdoms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This expreſly relates to the <hi>Prelacy</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> then in being and uſe in <hi>England</hi> (which was far from <hi>Apoſtolique</hi> and <hi>Primitive,</hi> as this Doctor, in his words before cited out of his Book of <hi>Tears, &amp;c.</hi> hath clearely confeſſed:) and to the extirpating of whatſoever in it ſavoured of <hi>Superſtition, Tyranny, Schiſm, Prophaneſs, Sinfulneſs,</hi> or was otherwiſe <hi>contrary to ſound Doctrine, or the power of godlineſs.</hi> If there be any other <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> truly <hi>Apoſtolique</hi> and <hi>Primitive,</hi> free from all theſe evils, and <hi>agreeable to ſound Doctrine, and the power of godlineſs,</hi> It is ſo far from the ſenſe and intention of this Covenant, to <hi>extirpate</hi> it, that it plainly includes rather a binding of all Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to endeavour, by all lawful and fit ways and means, to procure it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That herein, by the Doctors own allegations, <hi>all ſober honeſt men that rightly underſtand themſelves, and the true meaning of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, concur with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Himſelf ſaith, (pag. 22.) that the <hi>Covenant is no way in Conſcience to be ſtretched againſt a right and regular Epiſcopacy, no more than Phyſique given to cure a diſeaſe, ſhould like unmortified Quick ſilver, be applyed to kill the man.</hi> And this, he <hi>knows, was the ſenſe of the moſt learned men in the Aſſembly.</hi> And this, (he ſaith, pag. 23.) <hi>He hath often heard Mr.</hi> Marſhal
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>This may put him in mind, that hereupon, himſelf took the</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>which he now ſo much viliſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi>
                  </note>, <hi>and others affirm (who had a great hand in penning and promoting the Covenant) and they owned it to ſome Foraign Divines, That the Covenant was levelled at the</hi> (Deſpoticum, Tyrannicum regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) <hi>miſ-government, not the Government by Epiſcopacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which, he addes, <hi>This is at preſent, the ſenſe and hopes of the moſt learned and godly Presbyterians, whom I have lately ſpoken with in</hi> London <hi>and elſewhere,</hi> &amp;c. And a little after, he <hi>beſeecheth God, that by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties piety and wiſdom, (all thoſe materials which were good in that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, noble, and venerable fabrick of Epiſcopacy) may be ſpeedily and reſolutely ſetled in its beſt conſtitution: wherein, to take counſel, is King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152539:6"/>
               <p> But whereas, he there (pag. 23.) ſaith, that this was alſo the ſenſe <hi>of thoſe, who with himſelf, had as much right to ſit among them</hi> (that is, in the <hi>Aſſembly) as any others, but were not permitted, either by popular faction and tumult, or by other ſhufflings and reaſons of State; which took care to exclude or deter all the excellent Biſhops of the Church, and the moſt able of Epiſcopal Divines, for fear there ſhould have been any juſt plea for moderate Epiſcopacy, againſt the then Magiſtry of Presbytery:</hi> To this I muſt give this Anſwer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That I willingly accept of that part of this ſpeech, that this (to wit, what was before by him ſpoken, and by me alleged, touching the right <hi>Epiſcopacy)</hi> was the ſenſe of himſelf, and of thoſe that by his telling, <hi>had right to fit in the Aſſembly,</hi> to make out my preſent aſſertion of the <hi>concurrence</hi> of able men herein.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which he here affirmeth either of himſelf, or any others having <hi>right to ſit in the Aſſembly of Divines</hi> called by <hi>Ordinance</hi> of both Houſes of Parliament, dated <hi>June</hi> 12. 1643. that they <hi>were not permitted, either by popular faction and tumult, or by other ſhufflings,</hi> &amp;c. to <hi>fit,</hi> &amp;c. is a very great ſlander. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Touching himſelf, who (not now only, but heretofore) hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that he having as <hi>much right to ſit</hi> among the Divines in the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> as any others, was not permitted to ſit there. If he mean that <hi>he had as much right as any others,</hi> who were not at all choſen to ſit there, I admit what he ſaith, to be true. But, if he intend to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate that he was <hi>choſen,</hi> and yet not permitted to ſit, this is a loud un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth; for he being then (as I remember) Parſon of the <hi>Deanry</hi> of <hi>Bock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> (which albeit it be reputed to be worth 4 or 500 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> per an.</hi> yet he, to his ſhame, and the little honour of thoſe that imploy him, is non-reſident from it, and preacheth at the <hi>Temple:</hi>) was not choſen to be one of the <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> For, in <hi>Eſſex</hi> were choſen Mr. <hi>Stephen Marſhal of Finchingfield,</hi> Mr. <hi>Obadiah Sedgwick,</hi> then of <hi>Cogſhal,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Matthew Newcomen</hi> of <hi>Dedham.</hi> But this Doctor was choſen neither there, nor any where elſe, as by the Ordinance it ſelf is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to every eye that will peruſe it. And had it been otherwiſe, he had not been permitted, (as I can tell him in his ear) to have been ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the <hi>Aſſembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why ſhould he ſo much complain, and bewayle his <hi>not being permitted to ſit in that Aſſembly,</hi> which he ſo much vilifieth, and call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>A ſifted Sequatious Aſſembly</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Tears. <hi>&amp;c</hi> p. 213.</note>; <hi>a Scot-Engliſh Aſſembly which were as the grand Inqueſt, the Promoters or Apparitors to the Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<note n="d" place="margin">Pag. 334.</note>: Rabbies ſitting in</hi> Moſes <hi>Chair</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Ibid.</note>? And then, taking it for granted, that the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> were the <hi>Annotators</hi> on the Bible (which is altogether untrue) he chargeth them ſo, <hi>as if they were Chaplains at once ſerving the Lord, their Bellies and the times, as partaking of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the lord, and the Table of Devils</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Ibid pag. 334.</note>. I forbear to foul more paper
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152539:6"/>with the reſt of his <hi>Billinſgate</hi> Rhetorick beſtowed on that <hi>Aſſembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, mark the inference. He is angry that he, <hi>having right,</hi> was not permitted to ſit in that <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> Therefore, his anger, muſt needs be for this, that he could not be a <hi>Sequatious Aſſembly-man,</hi> one of the <hi>Grand Inqueſt, a Promoter and Apparitor of the Long Parliament, a Chaplain at once ſerving the Lord, his Belly, and the times,</hi> and <hi>a Partaker of the Table of Devils,</hi> as well as <hi>of the Lord.</hi> O what pity is it that he fate not! Surely, I have ſo much charity for him, (if I may judge of the tree by this fruit) as to believe, and profeſs, that if the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> had been ſuch as he deſcribeth it, he had better <hi>right to fit in it,</hi> then any that ſate there.</p>
               <p>Indeed, his laſt mentioned expreſſion of the Aſſembly as being <hi>Chaplains at once ſerving the Lord, their Bellies, and the Times,</hi> aroſe from his Bilious Paſſion at the <hi>Annotators</hi> for not finding a knot in a Bulruſh; and that from ſome Textst, hey did not brand that for <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,</hi> which he had done; whether thoſe Texts, condemn it, or not. But I muſt not further make an Excurſion upon this: but leave him to D. <hi>B.</hi> upon whom he hath beſtowed 10 whole leaves in <hi>Folio</hi> in that his ſcoulding <hi>Tears,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of his Mother</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">See p 685 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>, in nothing but raving, rayling, belying the Doctor, without affording one line in a ſerious, ſolid, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber confuting of either that Doctors <hi>Definition</hi> of <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> any Text of Scripture, or other Arguments or Reaſons for his opinion; or, to diſprove the ſame.</p>
               <p>But, you will ſay, what is that to me? I confeſs, this is a digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, therefore I will ſay no more, but onely adviſe Dr. <hi>John</hi> to ſpend half the time (if he can ſpare no more) in peruſing D. <hi>B.</hi> his ſecond Edition of that Tract of <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> (which D. <hi>J. G.</hi> cannot but have ſeen) that he hath trifled away in rayling upon D. <hi>B.</hi> and, to confute that Book, if he can; becauſe, as I hear, he hath promiſed ſo to do. This, if he will once perform, like a Scholar, and a Divine; then, whereas D. <hi>G.</hi> hath in his <hi>Sighs</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">pag. 664.</note>, &amp;c. ſaid (moſt gravely) that D. <hi>B.</hi> by his <hi>late purchaſe will give the world cauſe in after-ages, to look as narrowly to him, and his poſterity, how they thrive, as the Roman Souldiers did to the Jews Guts and Excrements, when they ſearched for the Gold which they had ſwallowed,</hi> as <hi>Joſephus
<note n="*" place="margin">De excid. Hieroſ.</note> tells us.</hi> I dare undertake, that then, if D. <hi>G.</hi> will either deſire to be the Groom of D. <hi>B.</hi> his Stool, or to be at the charge thereof, he ſhall have all that comes from him and his, without purloyning, or the leaſt diminution.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But, as to what he ſaith of <hi>others, having right to ſit,</hi> that they were <hi>not permitted, either by popular faction and tumult, or by other ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flings and reaſons of State, which took care to exclude or deter all the excellent Biſhops, and the moſt able of Epiſcopal Divines,</hi> &amp;c. is a moſt groſs and malicious <hi>untruth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, among thoſe that were choſen, and ſummoned to ſit in that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152539:7"/>
                  <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> what ſay you to Dr. <hi>Richard Love,</hi> Dr. <hi>Raph. Brownrig</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Exceter;</hi> D. <hi>Samuel Ward,</hi> Dr. <hi>John Harris,</hi> Dr. <hi>Robert Saunderſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Croſs, James Archbiſhop of Armagh,</hi> D. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias Styles,</hi> Dr. <hi>Featly,</hi> Dr. <hi>Chriſtopher Paſhly,</hi> Dr. <hi>John Hacket,</hi> Dr. <hi>Thomas Weſtfield</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> Dr. <hi>Henry Hammon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Rich. Oldſworth,</hi> and many moe? Where can you pick out three <hi>Biſhops,</hi> more <hi>excellent</hi> for learning and piety? or, other <hi>Epiſcopal Divines,</hi> more <hi>able?</hi> of 122 Divines choſen to <hi>ſit,</hi> there were 24 that never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared. And even in the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> ſome proteſted againſt the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of <hi>Primitive Epiſcopacy,</hi> of which Mr. <hi>Herbert Palmer</hi> was one. And Dr. <hi>Burges</hi> was ſuſpended from ſitting there, by the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> for declaring and proteſting againſt the firſt draught of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> brought into the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> for that (among other things) there was required an extirpation of <hi>Prelacy</hi> indefinitely and abſolutely, without either limitation, or explication.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe that came not, who <hi>excluded, or deterred them?</hi> they were all ſummoned, as appears by the Books of the <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> What hindred them? was it not either becauſe they liked not the Election, or the Perſons choſen to ſit with them; or, that they being for the late King, durſt not to ſit, either for fear of moleſtation by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or diſpleaſure of the King?</p>
               <p>For the manner of <hi>Election,</hi> it was no other for kind (although more Solemn and warrantable) than that antecedaneous choice, which the Lords had made of ſundry Lords, Biſhops and other Divines, to conſult at the Deans Houſe of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> touching reformation in matters of Religion; at which none then boggled, but all readily joyned in it.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>perſons choſen to ſit with them,</hi> they were all of them reputed to be able and pious, far beyond many that ſate in the uſual Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wherein ſometimes Lay-men (as Chancellors and Regiſters
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Witneſs the</hi> Chancelor <hi>and</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>of</hi> Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln, <hi>choſen at once to ſit in</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation <hi>in the laſt Kings reign: Which two, a great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor that knew them well, called</hi> Simeon <hi>and</hi> Levi; <hi>the</hi> Devil <hi>and his</hi> Damme: <hi>upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that their Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </note>) were admitted, as well as ſome members of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the late <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> So that if this offended them who now refuſed to ſit in it, the offence was rather taken, then given.</p>
               <p>And as for any fear of trouble from the Parliament, or of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his then Majeſty, it was but a pannick fear, without ground. For, being called by the Parliament, the Parliament was bound to protect them. Yea, had they not been ſo choſen, yet if they had continued ſober, quiet and peaceable, they needed not to have fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Parliament. Witneſs that quiet, ſober, prudent Dr. <hi>Juckson,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> who lived quietly, and without all danger of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or impriſonment, in the Parliament-Quarters; yet was he a man known to be firm to the King, in the greateſt diviſions and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between the King and Parliament: ſo might all theſe have done, carrying themſelves as he did.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152539:7"/>
               <p> And, as for the Kings diſpleaſure, there could be as little fear of that. For, he never was diſpleaſed with the Biſhop of <hi>Londons</hi> abode here; but highly reſpected and honoured him, to the laſt. It is true, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſate in the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> becauſe not choſen a Member of it. Yet the <hi>Prince Elector Palatine</hi> ſate there, without offence to his Majeſty. And albeit his Majeſty at firſt diſliked the calling and ſitting of that Aſſembly; yet afterwards, he liked and approved of what they had done, as appears by the <hi>Meſſage</hi> he ſent to both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>Octob.</hi> 11. 1648. wherein (among other things) he was pleaſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs himſelf touching the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> thus: <hi>As to that part of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition for the calling and ſitting of the Aſſembly of Divines, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſaith, That he will by Act of Parliament confirm the calling and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſaid Aſſembly ſince the firſt of</hi> July 1643. <hi>And that they ſhall have ſuch powers as are mentioned in the ſaid Ordinance. And that they ſhall continue their meeting and ſitting, and be diſſolved in ſuch manner as both Houſes of Parliament ſhall direct.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But enough of this ſecond point. It is ſufficient that the Doctor in the midſt of all his revilings and ſlanders, hath acknowledged ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to concur in the ture ſenſe of the Covenant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>III. PROPOSITION. <hi>That notwithstanding all that he hath ſpoken touching the true ſenſe of the Covenant, and ſo great a concurrence in it, he endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to vilifie, make odious, and to deſtroy the Covenant it ſelf, as his main deſign.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the entrance to his <hi>Anſwers</hi> and <hi>Solutions,</hi> for ſatisfying of <hi>all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and honeſt mens</hi> Conſciences, to take off <hi>their ſhyneſs of all</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> he begins thus, pag. 6. <hi>To prevent which ſad meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſis</hi> (that is, in turning Covenanters <hi>into pillars of Apoſtacies) in City and Country, my Anſwer and Reſolution in point of Conſcience, ſo far as it relates to Epiſcopacy, is this.</hi> But, in the Margent, he calls his Anſwers, <hi>oblique.</hi> And they are <hi>oblique</hi> indeed: for, he begins them, thus:</p>
               <p>Firſt, he boaſteth, that he can <hi>ſhrewdly batter the Covenant, by urging the defectiveneſs</hi> and <hi>invalidity</hi> of it, to <hi>bind,</hi> either in <hi>conſcience,</hi> or <hi>in any other Judicatory;</hi> becauſe, <hi>without the Kings conſent.</hi> Without this, it binds no more then the Vow of a <hi>Servant, Son, Daughter</hi> or <hi>Wife,</hi> could <hi>bind</hi> them <hi>without, yea againſt the declared</hi> conſent of their <hi>Maſter, Father</hi> or <hi>Husband, under whoſe protection they were,</hi> pag. 6. Here, ſee his good-will in this <hi>Battering Ram.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To prove this, he cites in his Margent, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2. which makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152539:8"/>him, as I ſhall after demonſtrate. Mean while, take notice, that his inſtances of <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Sons,</hi> is a Tale of a Tub: there is no ſuch thing. That Chapter mentions onely <hi>Daughters (in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, in their youth)</hi> and <hi>Wives</hi> that are under <hi>Husbands,</hi> when the <hi>Vow</hi> is made. Nor are their <hi>Vows</hi> void, for want of a <hi>declared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> (as he talks:) but, they are valid, if <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Husband, bearing</hi> them made, <hi>holdeth his peace,</hi> verſ. 4. and verſ. 7. Who will truſt ſuch a falſe man, that thus dares to falfifie an expreſs Text of Scripture?</p>
               <p>And whereas he cites in the Margent, <hi>Num.</hi> 30.2. to prove the <hi>invalidity</hi> of Vows of <hi>Servants, Sons, Daughters, Wives,</hi> as aforeſaid; that ſecond verſe expreſly makes againſt what he here alledged it for. His intention is to prove the Covenant <hi>invalid,</hi> becauſe taken by <hi>men,</hi> without the <hi>Royal conſent.</hi> To prove that, he produceth this Text. But, the Text ſpeaks onely of a <hi>Vow</hi> made by a <hi>man:</hi> and tells us, that all <hi>ſuch Vows</hi> are <hi>binding. If a MAN vow a vow unto the Lord, and ſwear an oath to bind his ſoul with a bond, he ſhall not break his word, he ſhall do according to all that proceedeth out of his mouth.</hi> Here is not the leaſt hint of any Exception, no not ſo much as of a <hi>Son,</hi> under his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but, all <hi>men</hi> that <hi>vow,</hi> are by God held unto it, whether the chief Governour conſent, or not: It is onely the <hi>vow</hi> of a <hi>woman,</hi> in <hi>mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> or <hi>Matrimony,</hi> which may be made void, as is manifeſt in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent verſes; but, not in that.</p>
               <p>As for his <hi>Eccho,</hi> and <hi>retorting the Violence and Noiſe of the times,</hi> and <hi>the Midwifery of tumults and Armies,</hi> upon <hi>the Covenant:</hi> His <hi>further urging the Novelty and partiality of it.</hi> Page 7. <hi>The ſad and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gique Effects,</hi> which he malitiouſly imputeth to the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf; the <hi>bafflings</hi> and annulling of it <hi>by Counter and groſs Engagements, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it had ſerved as one of the great Rocks for the late Kings Shipwrack:</hi> theſe are all ſuch nototious untruths, that nothing but impudence it ſelf raiſed to its Meridian, would dare to avouch, or own. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſs through this mire, without <hi>anſwering</hi> this wiſe Doctor <hi>according to his</hi> ſcurrilous <hi>folly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, as to his ſixth <hi>Oblique Anſwer,</hi> pag. 8. wherein, he ſaith, <hi>It is very conſiderable how the Covenant (if interpreted againſt all Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) muſt needs grate ſore upon, and pierce to the very quick, thoſe former</hi> lawful Oathes (where he takes it for granted that the <hi>Covenant</hi> is not lawful) <hi>not onely that of Allegiance and Supremacy, and Canonical Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;</hi> but, that of the <hi>King</hi> at his <hi>Coronation.</hi> And, he after adds, that there cannot be <hi>any Superfetation of ſuch a contradictory Vow and Covenant, without apparent perjury.</hi> I muſt here make bold to tell him, firſt, ſuppoſing the Covenant to be againſt <hi>all Epiſcopacy,</hi> what is that to the Oaths of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Aliegiance</hi> to his Majeſty? Can no man be true to <hi>Kings,</hi> but he that is for <hi>Biſhops?</hi> Verily, this very Doctor herein contradicts and confutes this abſurd Aſſertion, at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152539:8"/>pag. 25. where he ſaith, <hi>Doubtleſs the ſence of the Covenant hath lately quickned many mens Conſciences in the Allegiance to the King, ſo to bring him (as</hi> David) <hi>home with infinite joy and triumph.</hi> Who acted moſt in re-introducing the ſecluded Members, in procuring a free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in bringing home his preſent Majeſty, (whom God bleſs and preſerve) but <hi>Covenanteers?</hi> Nor is there any ſyllable in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant contrary to, but altogether conſiſtent with, and inciting to the moſt vigorous performance of thoſe two Oaths of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance.</hi> To charge therefore the <hi>Covenant</hi> as <hi>contradictory</hi> to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Oaths; and, as tending to <hi>apparent perjury,</hi> is ſuch manifeſt <hi>bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy</hi> againſt ſo ſacred an <hi>Oath of God,</hi> as cannot but be abhorred of all ſober Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Touching the Oath of <hi>Canonical Obedience to Biſhops:</hi> it is true, they took upon them to impoſe ſuch a tyrannical Yoke upon too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their brethren. But, <hi>quo jure?</hi> and how far were ſuch Oaths Obligatory? This was never found practiſed by <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Biſhops;</hi> nor warranted by any Law of this Land: but onely derived from the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> which here is limited by our <hi>Statute Laws;</hi> none of which do appoint or approve any ſuch Oath. Nor can it be expected, that if Epiſcopacy ſhould be reduced to the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Inſtitution,</hi> ſuch tyranny will ever be again endured. And as for that Oath, what doth it require, but obedience <hi>in omnibus licitis &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtis;</hi> which, our late Epiſcopacy leaſt cared for? The <hi>Laws</hi> tye all men to things <hi>lawful and honeſt.</hi> And, if ſo, then the ſame Doctor hath furniſhed me with an Argument (ſtrong enough to retort upon the Author of it) againſt that <hi>Canonical Oath,</hi> which himſelf urgeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Covenant,</hi> pag. 15. (inverting onely the name of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> into that of this <hi>Oath:) They are not the bare words of the Oath of Canonical Obedience, which as Charms, can bind any mans Conſcience to or againſt any thing; but it is the force of Truth, Reaſon, Juſtice, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Duty to God and man, our ſelves or others, which morally and really obligeth men, either by Gods general or particular Precepts; which are as Iron and Adamantine Bands on every mans ſoul, to chuſe good and do it, to hate evil, and eſchew it, long before any of theſe withes or cords of mans combining or tying, are put upon them.</hi> By which he argues the needleſneſs of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> and ſo do I, of the unwarranted <hi>Oath of Canonical Obedience.</hi> And if this Oath ſhould be extended to obey ſuch Biſhops as <hi>Wren, Peirce,</hi> and others, in all they of late enjoyned, there is much more cauſe to conclude againſt it, then againſt the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> (though it ſhould be extended to extirpation of all <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi>) in the words of this Doctor, pag. 8. <hi>It is therein of no bond or validity, as to any good mans Conſcience.</hi> And ſo farewel ſuch an <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And touching the <hi>Kings Oath,</hi> there is nothing obliging him further then to preſerve that Government; ſo far as it is agreeable to, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152539:9"/>warranted by the holy Scripture, and <hi>Primitive Inſtitution:</hi> ſo far he condeſcended at the <hi>Iſle of Wight.</hi> And who requireth more? And yet, even this alſo <hi>may be changed, by his Royal Aſſent to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Deſire of the two Houſes of Parliament;</hi> as this Doctor doth more then tacitely admit, pag. 18. Cannot the Legiſlative Power change Government by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as well as <hi>abrogate</hi> other <hi>Laws?</hi> This is to charge ſome with <hi>perjury,</hi> which he dareth not to name: to fright others with a ſcare-Crow, or man of Clouts; and, to condemn all the Churches of Chriſt that have laid Epiſcopacy aſide.</p>
               <p>His next <hi>Quarrel</hi> at the <hi>Covenant,</hi> (if it abjure all Epiſcopacy) is this, That it <hi>runs us upon a great Rock, not onely of Novelty, but of Schiſm; and daſheth us, both in opinion and practiſe, againſt the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Cuſtome of the Catholique Church, in all places and ages (till of latter years
<note n="*" place="margin">He means till <hi>Calvin.</hi> See his <hi>Dendrology</hi> in his <hi>ſighs, tears,</hi> &amp;c:</note>) from the Apoſtles days.</hi> This he often harps upon in a Magiſterial Traditionary way. But, once prove <hi>that our aboliſhed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy was of ſo antient and univerſal Obſervation; Et eris mihi Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Apollo.</hi> Whoever will but read <hi>the judgement</hi> of Doctor <hi>John Reynolds</hi> concerning Epiſcopacy, expreſſed in a Letter to Sir <hi>Francis Knolls,</hi> in the year 1598. and Dr. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhers</hi> Tract, called, <hi>The Reduction of Epiſcopacy,</hi> propoſed in the year 1641. will ſoon find this mans bold Aſſertion to dwindle into a vapor.</p>
               <p>In the eighth place,
<note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> under colour of propounding the <hi>Loyal</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ſenſe of it; he daſheth it with <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> to be taken at all: For, when he would have men to <hi>retire to the ſober ſenſe wherein alone it might lawfully be taken,</hi> he addeth an Alloy; <hi>If it had been impoſed by due Authority.</hi> This ſheweth his denial of the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of it. And ſo, in ſtead of ſatisfying a ſcrupulous Conſcience how to take the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant a right, he cunningly deterreth from the taking of it at all: is not this Jugling? By <hi>due Authority,</hi> he meaneth <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> as is clear by his next <hi>Anſwer;</hi> in examining whereof, I ſhall endeavour to lay open the weakneſs and falſhood of this ſuggeſtion.</p>
               <p>Ninthly,
<note place="margin">Pag. 0.</note> he tells you, <hi>It were eaſie to level to the ground all thoſe fair, but fallacious pretences drawn to fortifie the Covenant, from Scripture-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, wherein the Jews ſometimes ſolemnly renewed their Covenant with God: But, it was that expreſs Covenant which God himſelf had firſt made with them in</hi> Horeb <hi>and Mount</hi> Sinai, <hi>punctually preſcribed by God to</hi> Moſes, <hi>and by</hi> Moſes <hi>(as their Supreme Governour or King) impoſed upon them. This, they ſometimes renewed, after they had broken it by their Apoſtacy to falſe and ſtrange gods. But this was not the caſe of the Church or people of</hi> England, <hi>nor was there any need of ſuch covenanting, any more then there was any</hi> Moſes, <hi>or</hi> Hezekiah, <hi>or</hi> Joſiah, <hi>or any chief Governour commanding it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Hatlot is forward to call her <hi>Whore,</hi> firſt, with whom ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſty quarrelleth; ſo this Deceiver cries out upon the <hi>fallaciouſneſs</hi> of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152539:9"/>the <hi>Covenant,</hi> becauſe he ſeeks fallaciouſly to take off all men from it. In this reviling of his, there are falſhoods enow. I will inſtance in ſome.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is falſe that there was no Covenant, but of Gods own <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing;</hi> and, ſecondly, that he preſcribed but <hi>one.</hi> I ſhall, for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, diſcover the falſhood of both theſe together. If none, but of his <hi>preſcribing,</hi> what meaneth that of this Doctors own quoting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Num.</hi> 30.2. which was <hi>ſpontaneous?</hi> What, that of <hi>Joſhua, and the Princes of the Congregation,</hi> with the cheating <hi>Gibeonites? Joſh.</hi> 9.15. And, what that (to omit ſundry other) <hi>of the children of Iſrael and the children of Judah</hi> (after the Babyloniſh Captivity) <hi>who joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord in a perpetual Covenant, never to be forgotten?</hi> Jer. 50.5. Theſe were all ſeveral Covenants, of different kinds; none of them <hi>preſcribed,</hi> yet all of them allowed (and the breach of them pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed) by God. To this, may be added, what the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> in their Reaſons againſt the <hi>Covenant</hi> by general conſent in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, June</hi> 1. 1647. Sect. 2. pag. 2, 3. ſaith for it ſelf, that they are unſatisfied, becauſe the Covenant is <hi>impoſed,</hi> which is <hi>repugnant to the nature of a Covenant; which being a contract, implyeth a voluntary mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual conſent of the Contractors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo falſe, that the <hi>Covenant</hi> on <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> was <hi>impoſed</hi> by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> (as the <hi>Supreme Governour or King) on the people.</hi> For <hi>Moſes</hi> was no more their <hi>Supreme Governour or King,</hi> then <hi>Samuel,</hi> to whom the people impetuouſly cryed for a <hi>King, to judge them like all the Nations</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.5.</note>, when <hi>the Lord himſelf was their King</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">1 Sam. 12 12.</note>.</p>
               <p>Nor did <hi>Moſes,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> himſelf impoſe that Covenant in <hi>Horeb,</hi> as their <hi>Supreme</hi> Governour, if <hi>Moſes</hi> may be believed. For he tells us, that <hi>The Lord talked with them face to face, in the Mount, out of the midſt of the fire. Moſes,</hi> onely <hi>ſtood between the Lord and them, at that time, to ſhew them the word of the Lord.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 5.4 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And albeit there was but one <hi>Legal Covenant,</hi> yet what was the <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the <hi>Paſſeover;</hi> and many moe made, or lawful to be made, (and ſundry of them to be renewed alſo; as, the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> and other <hi>Feſtivals</hi>) by ſuch ſolemn <hi>preſcribing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas he <hi>bleſſeth God</hi> (as they that <hi>bleſs an idol</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Eſay 66.3.</note>) that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy to falſe and ſtrange gods, was not the caſe of the Church or people of</hi> England, ſo as to take riſe from thence, to enter into this <hi>Covenant:</hi> I deſire him to tell me, what meant the falling off of ſundry Biſhops to too much Popery both in Doctrine (witneſs all their <hi>Arminian</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, which the learned <hi>Bannes,</hi> and other <hi>Dominican</hi> Papiſts diſclaim, and confute:) and alſo in the general practice in Cathedrals, and elſewhere, the ſetting up of <hi>Altars, Tapers, Candles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(deviſed by mans fancies:)</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Injuct.</hi> 3.</note> which laſt (among other things) is in the <hi>Queens In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions,</hi> affirmed to <hi>tend to Idolatry and Superſtition; which of all other
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152539:10"/>offences, God Almighty doth moſt deteſt and abhor, for that the ſame dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh moſt his honour and glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like may be ſaid of the late <hi>Church-Muſique, Anthemes,</hi> &amp;c. ſung with ſo much curioſity, quavering, tautologies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the hearers cannot underſtand any part of the matter which is ſung. A thing which not only the judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> cenſured and condemned; but the late Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> provided againſt, <hi>Injunct.</hi> 49. by enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning only modeſt and diſtinct <hi>ſongs to be ſo uſed in all parts of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayers in the Church, that it may be as plainly underſtood, as if it were read without ſinging.</hi> And even where <hi>Muſick, at the beginning, or ending of Common-prayer,</hi> was <hi>permitted,</hi> it was further provided, that if an <hi>Hymn</hi> were <hi>ſung,</hi> care ſhould be taken that it might be ſo done, as to be <hi>underſtood and perceived.</hi> And where this is not ſo done, ſee the cenſure of the <hi>Homily</hi> of the <hi>place and time of Prayer,</hi> part 2. where ſuch <hi>chaunting and playing upon Organs,</hi> are ſaid to have <hi>diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God ſo ſore, and filthily defiled his holy Houſe, and his place of Prayer, that for it he juſtly deſtroyed many Nations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſay nothing of the many thouſands of <hi>Popiſh</hi> families in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the ſwarms of <hi>Prieſts, Jeſuites</hi> and other Emiſſaries of the <hi>Pope,</hi> that at all times creep in, not only into Widows houſes, but into Noble-mens and Princes Houſes, to ſeduce, and draw more and more men and women off from the truth to Superſtition and Idolatry every day.
<note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> There is therefore cauſe enough to make ſuch a <hi>Covenant.</hi> But, where he addeth, That this <hi>Covenant</hi> was but <hi>the petty compoſition of a few Politique men, very</hi> mean Subjects <hi>ſome of them, either as</hi> Lawyers, <hi>or</hi> Miniſters, <hi>a great part of whom, he, and others knew to be no very great Clerks or States-men; and fitter for a</hi> Country Cure, <hi>then to contrive and compoſe Solemn Leagues and Covenants,</hi> &amp;c. adding, that <hi>their beads, rather then their hearts, and their State-correſpondencies more then their Conſciences, brought forth this Covenant.</hi> I ſhall not retort, that there be not none who know him to be ſuch an one himſelf: but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, deſire all, to pity and pray for him. This railing vein is ſo incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into his proud felleous heart, that there is no hope of curing it, but by ſlighting ſuch palpable ſcornings, and praying for the <hi>ſcorner,</hi> that the Lord may either heal, or <hi>rebuke</hi> him
<note n="n" place="margin">Zech. 3.2.</note>.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, He confidently (I will not ſay, not for want of ignorance) a voucheth, that <hi>there is no</hi> precept <hi>or</hi> patern <hi>for any ſuch in all the</hi> New Teſtament, <hi>nor in all ſucceeding ages;</hi> and that <hi>we never read, nor heard of any Covenanting Chriſtians (until the Holy League</hi> (meaning that of bloudy Papiſts to deſtroy the <hi>Hugonotes,</hi> as they termed the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) <hi>in France</hi>) except that of <hi>Baptiſm — this is the New and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Covenant of all true Chriſtians: this</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>we break by wilful and preſumptuous ſins; and renew by true repentance and worthy participation of the Lords Supper.</hi> Then he proceeds, ſaying; <hi>How
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152539:10"/>vaſtly different from this ſacred Covenant,
<note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> this late piece of Policy more then Piety is,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he leaves to all ſober minded Chriſtians to judge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, That if there were no <hi>precept,</hi> nor <hi>patern</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> it is ſufficient if there be any in the <hi>Old;</hi> if not <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical,</hi> or meerly <hi>Typical:</hi> unleſs this Doctor be turned <hi>Antinomian.</hi> For, <hi>all Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.16. This is meant of the <hi>Old,</hi> as well as <hi>New Teſtament. For, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures, might have hope,</hi> Rom. 15.4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What meaneth he by this <hi>Covenant?</hi> Is it his meaning, that there is no precept nor patern for Covenanting againſt our <hi>Engliſh E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy?</hi> (there is not any for it, ſay I.) Nor is it much material, that he hath found none againſt it, for we can find no ſuch <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in the New Teſtament; nor, warranted by it; notwithſtanding all his common talk in this Book, and elſewhere. But this Gentleman muſt be pleaſed to look upon this Covenant, not only as againſt his adored Epiſcopacy, but in the full Latitude, as being extended <hi>againſt Popery, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneſs, and whatſoever is contrary to ſound Doctrine and the power of godlineſs</hi> in our ſelves as well as others: And, for the <hi>Preſervation</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> of Religion againſt the Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as likewiſe <hi>to preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties perſon and Authority, to diſcover all Incendiaries, Hinderers of the Reformation of Religion</hi> (beware, Doctor) <hi>Dividers between the King and his People, or one of the Kingdoms from the other;</hi> to endeavour the <hi>continuance</hi> of the happy <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Peace</hi> between them; <hi>to aſſiſt and defend all that have taken it, in the maintaining and purſuance thereof;</hi> to be <hi>unfainedly humbled for our own ſins, and for the ſins of theſe Kingdoms,</hi> and to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour for our ſelves and all others under our charge, in all duties to God and man, to amend our lives, and each one to go before another in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a real Reformation.</hi> This is the ſum of that <hi>Covenant</hi> (which each man promiſeth to obſerve, <hi>in and according to their ſeveral places and callings only</hi>) that this man ſo much ſetteth at naught, ſpurneth at, and does what he can to cauſe all men to throw off and abominate, meerly upon that one ſingle clauſe of <hi>extirpating the late Hierarchy,</hi> if ſo intended, as, for the future, to keep out all ſuch Epiſcopacy as he would have to be retroduced, although he never particularly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, nor ſetteth forth what that is.</p>
               <p>And now, <hi>I might leave it to all ſober Chriſtians to judge,</hi> whether this <hi>Covenant (taken in the preſence of Almighty God, the ſearcher of all hearts, with a true intention to perform the ſame, as all that take it ſhall anſwer at that great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed,)</hi> be a <hi>piece of Policy more then of Piety;</hi> And how little it differs from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152539:11"/>that <hi>ſacred Covenant</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> wherein every man <hi>ſtipulateth,</hi> and Covenanteth to <hi>deny all ungodlineſs and wordly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Tit. 2.12.</note>?</p>
               <p>What other in effect and ſubſtance is our preſent folemn League and Covenant? And dares this Seraphical <hi>Doctor</hi> to ſay, that this could not be <hi>lawfully taken,</hi> for want of <hi>due Authority to impoſe</hi> it? doth not God require as much? hath not he impoſed all theſe things upon all Chriſtians? are not they all called upon by God himſelf to <hi>Vow</hi> all theſe unto <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>to pay them</hi> too? What then can it be leſs then deſo rate madneſs, to throw off ſuch a Covenant?</p>
               <p>And is there <hi>no precept or patern</hi> to warrant ſuch a <hi>Covenant</hi> in the <hi>New teſtament?</hi> what is the meaning of that, ſpoken to men under the <hi>Baptiſmal-covenant</hi> before; <hi>Give your ſelves unto God, as thoſe that are alive from the dead?</hi> Rom. 6.13. What is it to <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith which was once delivered to the Saints
<note n="p" place="margin">Jude 3.</note>, in nothing terrified by the adverſaries</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 1.28</note>? Are not theſe <hi>precepts</hi> (together with that in <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. before mentioned) warrant enough to Vow and Covenant, again and again, to do all this? And as for <hi>Paterns,</hi> what ſaith our Doctor to that of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> namely, their <hi>giving themſelves firſt to the Lord;</hi> and then, unto <hi>Paul, by the will of God</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 8.5</note>? Nay, what ſaith he to <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, joyning with <hi>thoſe four men that had a vow upon them
<note n="s" place="margin">Act. 21.23</note>; whom Paul</hi> (by advice <hi>of James and all the Elders that were preſent</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> took, <hi>and the next day purifying himſelf with them, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Temple, to ſignifie the accompliſhment of the days of purifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Verſ. 26.</note>? If it be ſaid this was a <hi>Ceremonial Covenant:</hi> I reply, If <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf held it lawful (even when <hi>thoſe vows</hi> were to be at an end) for avoiding of ſcandal among weak brethren, or malicious perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Jews, to enter ſuch a Vow (which he had upon him after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.10.) without any impoſition of God or man, even under the Goſpel: then much more would he allow ſuch a <hi>Covenant</hi> as this, being altogether <hi>Evangelical.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whereas he will allow but one <hi>Covenant,</hi> to wit, <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> in the Goſpel; and this being <hi>broken by wilful and preſumptuous ſins, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by true repentance, and worthy participation of the Lords Supper:</hi> there are in this almoſt as many groſs errors, as words.</p>
               <p>For, firſt, Is not the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> a Goſpel-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as well as <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> Did ever any intelligent Divine either deny this, or affirm it to be a <hi>renewing</hi> of the other, and not a <hi>Covenant</hi> in it ſelf? Secondly, Do true Chriſtians, truly entred into the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Covenant,</hi> break it by <hi>wilful and preſumptuous ſins?</hi> I had thought that <hi>he that is born of God,</hi> doth <hi>not</hi> (ſo) <hi>ſin,</hi> for that <hi>his ſeed remaineth in him:</hi> yea, <hi>that he cannot</hi> (ſo) ſin, <hi>becauſe he is born of God</hi>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">1 Joh. 3.9.</note>: and that, though he <hi>doth what he hateth;</hi> yet, <hi>not allowing</hi> it, nor <hi>wilfully and preſumptuouſly,</hi> but out <hi>of weakneſs, (being led into captivity)</hi> doing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152539:11"/>
                  <hi>what he would not, it is no more he that doth it, but ſin that dwelleth in him</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 7.16, 17.</note>. Thirdly, Doth <hi>Repentance</hi> take off <hi>wilful and preſumptuous ſins?</hi> In the Law there was no <hi>Sacrifice</hi> appointed for ſuch ſins: yea, God made a Law, that <hi>he that ſinned preſumptuouſly, ſhould die the death</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>. And in the Goſpel, if we believe the Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> we are taught, that <hi>if we ſin wilfully, after that we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> (no not of Chriſt himſelf) <hi>for ſin, but a fearful looking for of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and fiery indignation, which ſhall devour the adverſaries</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 10.26, 27.</note>. Fourthly, Doth <hi>Repentance renew</hi> our <hi>Covenant</hi> made in <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> Surely, no more then it reneweth <hi>the remiſſion of our ſins:</hi> which, not <hi>Repentance,</hi> but Chriſt, in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> beſtoweth upon us once for all
<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 2.38.</note>: <hi>For he, by one offering, hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 10.14.</note>. Repentance recovereth the ſenſe of Gods favour and pardon, but doth not give a new remiſſion. Again, fifthly, <hi>The Lords Supper</hi> doth not renew our Baptiſmal Covenant as to <hi>remiſſion of ſin,</hi> but ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth us, on Chriſts part, to perform our Covenant in Baptiſm; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neweth our Vows on our part, to perform it better: therefore it is called, <hi>The Communion of the body and blood of Chriſt, whereby, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many, are made one bread, and one body, becauſe we are thereby par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that one bread
<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 10 16, 17.</note>; of which he that eateth, ſhall live for ever</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Joh. 6.51</note>. By this means, <hi>We grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Chriſt</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.15.</note>. Sixthly, <hi>The Lords Supper</hi> is not to be renewed, or taken again and again, for renewing our <hi>Baptiſmal Covenant,</hi> becauſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>wilful and preſumptuous ſins;</hi> but, for the renewing of our thankful remembrance of his death
<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor 11.26.</note>; for our more full <hi>Communion with him, by partaking of him</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 10</note>, and <hi>encreaſe in him, till we come to a perfect man, to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.14.</note>.</p>
               <p>I have inſiſted on this the longer, becauſe theſe few words ſavour ſtrongly of <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> and <hi>Popery.</hi> I ſhall make amends by <hi>brevity</hi> in the reſt. Whereas he tells us, pag. 13. that <hi>there is neither Law of God or man, requiring, impoſing or comprobating any ſuch Covenant;</hi> and that <hi>it appears at beſt, to be but a matter of Will-Worſhip of humane and private invention, void of publick and plenary injunction, eſteemed by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to be but as a ſtratagem of State, a flag of Faction, an Engine framed on purpoſe to batter down Epiſcopacy, and to ſeize their Eſtates, and all the Patrimony of the Church, to the great enriching of ſome Sacrilegious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> &amp;c. and, <hi>to the great joy of the Romiſh Party and Jeſuites,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who are thought by many wiſe men to have been, if not the</hi> Sires, <hi>yet the</hi> Sibs <hi>to that Covenant.</hi> This, and much more, is ſo full of railing, that no wiſe man will hold it other then folly to beſtow a Line in Anſwer to it. If this be not <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> I know not what is. As for his fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent prating of <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> here, in his <hi>Sermons,</hi> in his long, tedious
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152539:12"/>Ink-horn, <hi>Tears, Sighs,</hi> &amp;c. I know none ſo like unto <hi>Doeg,</hi> as this falſe vain-glorious man, whoſe <hi>tongue</hi> (and pen) <hi>deviſe miſchief, like a ſharp Raſor, working deceitfully: loving evil more then good, and lying rather then to ſpeak righteouſneſs.</hi> For this point, I again refer him to Doctor <hi>Burges,</hi> whoſe Book making it out that it is <hi>no Sacrilege nor Sin to buy ſuch Lands,</hi> ſtill lies unanſwered: and yet men go on with their cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and railings, as if nothing had been offered to ſtop their mouths who can ſwallow Church Lands formerly alienated, without the leaſt regret.</p>
               <p>But whereas he ſaith, pag. 24. <hi>This Age is the firſt Parent of that Prodigie, wherein Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians, either Presbyters or People, did perſecute godly Biſhops (of the ſame Faith and Profeſſion) yea, and Epiſcopacy it ſelf, though never ſo regular and reformed:</hi> I muſt crave leave to ſay, That however <hi>Godly Biſhops</hi> have heretofore been perſecuted unto death, in divers former ages of the Church; yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they perſecuted <hi>by Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians,</hi> but by enemies to the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs.</hi> Nor did any <hi>Orthodox and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſtians, either Presbyters or People, perſecute any godly Biſhops of this age.</hi> This therefore is a mere calumny and ſlander. It is true, that ſome <hi>Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians,</hi> did exhibit and proſecute Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Wren,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Peirce,</hi> two (if not all of them) being charged with no leſs than <hi>High Treaſon:</hi> the firſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being found guilty, was executed <hi>Jan.</hi> 10. 1644. The other two never anſwered the Articles exhibited againſt them unto this day, nor vindicated themſelves of thoſe Aſperſions caſt upon them, for being the prime and moſt active, and officious Inſtruments of <hi>Laud,</hi> to ſet the Church on fire; by means whereof, all the reſt of the Biſhops ſped the worſe.</p>
               <p>How <hi>godly</hi> theſe were, I know not; but this Doctor hath been the Proctor, and Advocate of <hi>Laud</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sighs,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 628.</note>, and Doctor <hi>Wren</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">pag. 634.</note>, highly applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in oppoſition to the charge of the Houſe of Commons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: and that he might lick clean him that was a known <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,</hi> (his hand being in) he beſtows a Vindication or Apologie, even for the late Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> Doctor <hi>Goodman</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">pag. 637</note> alſo; only he could find nothing to ſay for Biſhop <hi>Peirce,</hi> though he ſo devoutly <hi>thanked God that he had put down all the Lectures in his Dioceſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There were, no doubt, ſome of thoſe Biſhops which he alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth, that were learned and pious. But let him name one of thoſe (unleſs ſuch as were trapann'd by <hi>Williams,</hi> and other Capritious Pragmaticks, to have their hands in that high and unparliamentary <hi>Petition and Proteſtation to the late King and Houſe of Peers,</hi> in Dec. 1641.) that were ever in the leaſt perſecuted, and not rather honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (if learned and indeed godly) by <hi>Orthodox and reformed Chriſtians,</hi> whether <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>People.</hi> If any of them ſuffered with the reſt, in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152539:12"/>aboliſhing of ſuch <hi>Prelacy,</hi> they may thank thoſe other ruffling, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious, violent Ringleaders before named; and not blame others who could not help it, nor longer endure the ſlavery and perſecution which thoſe <hi>Amaziah-like Prieſts</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Amos.</note>, and Tyrants, had exerciſed over them. I now proceed to my laſt <hi>Propoſition,</hi> which is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <head>IIII. PROPOSITION. <hi>That, maugre all this mans calumnies, and malicious aſperſions, the Covenant, (even as to the point of that Hierarchical Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy lately laid aſide,) is to be conſtantly and conſcienciouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and kept, in the right ſenſe thereof, by all that have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, as they will avoid destruction here, and damnation hereafter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rus ſermo,</hi> you will ſay: <hi>this is an hard ſaying.</hi> But, not more <hi>hard</hi> then <hi>true.</hi> I ſhall make it out, thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If it were a Covenant made between man and man, God will require performance, or ſeverely puniſh the breach of it. We ſee this in the breach of the Covenant made by <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Iſrael: Joſh.</hi> 9.15. Although they obtained it by a wile, and by a lye. By a <hi>wile,</hi> in coming in <hi>old ſhooes and clouted, and old garments upon them, and all the bread of their proviſion, was dry and mouldy,</hi> ver. 5. By <hi>a lye,</hi> ſeveral times repeated, in ſaying, they <hi>came from a far;</hi> yea, <hi>a very far country,</hi> verſ. 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereas after the Covenant made, their <hi>lying</hi> appeared, and they were diſcovered, <hi>at the end of three days,</hi> to be <hi>their neighbours, and that they dwelt among them.</hi> All the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Iſrael, would hereupon have ſmitten and deſtroyed them, they being ſuch as by Gods command were to have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by <hi>Joſhua</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Verſ. 24.</note>, and had now ſo baſely cheated <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and all Iſrael. This the Princes would not ſuffer; whereupon all <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation murmured againſt the Princes: But all the Princes ſaid to all the Congregation, We have ſworn unto them by the Lord God of Iſrael; now therefore we may not touch them,</hi> ver. 18, 19. This quieted the people for the preſent, and for a long time after. Howbeit <hi>Saul,</hi> in an humor of envy or malice, many hundred years after <hi>ſlew the Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites,</hi> which then he found in Iſrael. But Gods anger was ſo kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at this, that he ſmote all the Land with a <hi>famine,</hi> for <hi>three years</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, even towards the latter end of <hi>Davids</hi> reign. And when <hi>David enquired of the Lord,</hi> the cauſe of this ſore Plague, <hi>The Lord anſwered, It is for Saul, and his bloudy houſe, becauſe he ſlew the Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> 2 Sam. 21.1. To appeaſe this wrath, <hi>ſeven</hi> of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſons, were demanded, and <hi>hanged before the Lord,</hi> ver. 9. — <hi>And after that, the Lord was entreated for the Land,</hi> ver. 14.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152539:13"/>
               <p> Now, if God were ſo ſevere for the breach of ſuch a deceitfully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Covenant between man and man, when they that procured it, were ſo baſe and falſe as our Doctor would make the late <hi>Covenant</hi> contrivers, and deſtined to deſtruction by God himſelf by that very hand which made that League with them: How ſinful and dangerous muſt it needs be, for men, upon any pretence whatſoever, to depart from, or wilfully to break any Covenant made with God himſelf! Here was no preſcribing of the <hi>League</hi> by God, nor <hi>force</hi> upon <hi>Joſhua</hi> or <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Yet God would not put up the breach of it, even upon the poſterity of a treacherous Crew that had meerly cheated all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at once.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is no Covenant made between man and man, but it is the <hi>Oath</hi> of God, and <hi>his Covenant.</hi> So, that Oath and Covenant made between the King and his Subjects, is called, <hi>The Oath of God,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.2. thus the Oath and Covenant of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> made with the <hi>King of Babylon,</hi> (an Idolater, and an enemy of God and all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) is by God himſelf called, <hi>Mine Oath, and my Covenant,</hi> Ezek. 17.19. And upon this account it was, that <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the Princes of Iſrael, ſwearing <hi>by the Name of the Lord God,</hi> they durſt not to touch the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites.</hi> Therefore all ſuch Covenants are irrevocable, and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable. If any man ſhall break them, he is ſure to be ruined. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> though a <hi>King,</hi> and though forced by the <hi>King of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> who had conquered <hi>Judah,</hi> laid aſide the rightful King thereof, <hi>Jehojakim,</hi> and ſet up <hi>Mattaniah</hi> (Uncle to <hi>Jehojahim</hi>) whom he call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Zedekiah</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">2 Kin. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.27.</note>, and <hi>made him ſwear by God,</hi> to be a Tributary to him; yet, <hi>rebelled againſt him,</hi> 2 Chron. 36.13. His rebellion was, his <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Ambaſſadours into Egypt, that they might give him Horſes, and much people,</hi> to arm himſelf to throw off the yoke of the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> to whom he had ſworn to be ſubject, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17.15. Now, much might have been ſaid for this. That <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was an enemy, a great Tyrant over the people of God, who were <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, and that were not to be <hi>in bondage to any man.</hi> And the <hi>Covenant</hi> was impoſed on him by force, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, all this notwithſtanding, mark how God takes this breach of ſuch a forc'd Covenant as this: <hi>Shall he break the Covenant, and be delivered?</hi> Nay, now he that cared not for his Oath, makes God himſelf to ſwear his ruine: <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, ſurely in the place where the King dwelleth, that made him King, whoſe Oath he deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and whoſe Covenant he brake, even with him, in the midſt of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon he ſhall die. Neither ſhall Pharaoh with his mighty Army, and great company, make for him in the war, by caſting up mounts, and building forts to cut off many perſons. Seeing he deſpiſed the Oath by breaking the Covenant, (when lo, he had given his hand) and hath done all theſe things, he ſhall not eſcape. Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God,</hi> (again) <hi>As I live,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152539:13"/>ſurely mine Oath that he hath deſtiſed, and my Covenant that he hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, even it I will recompence upon his own head. And I will ſpread my not upon him, and he ſhall be taken in my ſnare, and I will bring him to Babylon, and will plead with him there for his treſpaſs that he hath treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt ME. And all his fugitives</hi> (ſuch as firſt counſelled him to break that Covenant) <hi>and all his bands.</hi> (that adhered to him in that war) <hi>ſhall fall by the Sword; and they that remain, ſhall be ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad towards all winds. And ye ſhall know that I the Lord have ſpoken it:</hi> Verſ. 16.17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</p>
               <p>By this it is clear as the Sun, that God will never put up the wilful breach of any <hi>Covenant,</hi> but dreadfully puniſh it, even upon Kings themſelves; and will extend his wrath not onely upon themſelves, but upon all that counſel them to it, (Take heed, Doctor) and joyn with them in it. <hi>Of how much ſorer puniſhment then ſuppoſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy,</hi> who ſhall dare to trample under feet any Covenant made with God himſelf, in what manner ſoever, <hi>as an unholy thing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor will this end with temporal plagues in this life; but in <hi>Hell</hi> hereafter, although the <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Oath</hi> were but <hi>voluntary,</hi> and not <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</hi> For the breach of ſuch an Oath, Vow, or Covenant, is a ſin; and <hi>the wages of ſin is death</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 6.23</note>; not onely natural, but <hi>eternal,</hi> if not repented of. That this is <hi>a ſin,</hi> appears plainly by Gods own Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.21. <hi>When thou ſhalt vow a vow unto the Lord thy God, thouſhalt not ſlack to pay it: for the Lord thy God will ſurely require it of thee, and it would be ſin in thee;</hi> to wit, <hi>not to pay it;</hi> yea, to be <hi>ſlack to pay it.</hi> And that this is meant of even <hi>a voluntary vow,</hi> appears in verſ. 22. <hi>But if thou ſhalt forbear to vow, it ſhall be no ſin in thee.</hi> Wherefore, he addeth, verſ. 23. <hi>That which is gone out of thy lips, thou ſhalt keep and perform; even a free-will offering, according as thou haſt vowed unto the Lord thy God, which thou haſt promiſed with thy mouth.</hi> Can there be a clearer proof?</p>
               <p>Take one more, that <hi>by two or three witneſſes, every word may be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi> It is that of the <hi>Preacher,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.4, 5. <hi>When thou voweſt a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he hath no pleaſure in fools,</hi> (which, with God, are <hi>wicked men,</hi> Pſalm 73.3.) <hi>Pay that which thou haſt vowed. Better is it that thou ſhouldeſt not vow, then that thou ſhouldſt vow, and not pay.</hi> This therefore makes it out, that it is <hi>a ſin</hi> not to perform a voluntary vow. Now, leſt, after a vow, the <hi>Covenanter</hi> ſhould not think to evade his vow, by pleading, that he did it raſhly, and it was an errour in him ſo to do; it is added, by way of <hi>anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> verſ. 6. <hi>Suffer not thy mouth to cauſe thy fleſh to ſin, neither ſay thou before the Angel, that it was an errour. Wherefore ſhould God be angry at thy voice,</hi> (that is, wherefore ſhouldſt thou anger him by ſo ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?) <hi>and deſtroy the work of thy hands?</hi> It being now plain that this is a ſin, it cannot be denyed, that a wilful continued breach of a <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152539:14"/>Vow and Covenant,</hi> if not duely repented of, will certainly <hi>end in Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, Theſe inſtances are of particular and private perſons: what is this, to prove the like <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> and <hi>danger</hi> of the breach, or throwing off of a <hi>National Oath, League, and Covenant,</hi> not impoſed by <hi>due,</hi> or <hi>Supreme Authority?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Obligation</hi> of an Oath or Covenant, conſiſteth not in the Paucity or multitude of thoſe that enter into it, but in the making uſe of God in it; and his declaration thereupon. This was a tye upon all <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the <hi>ſwearing</hi> to the perfidious <hi>Gibeonites, by the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> as we have ſhewed before. Hence that of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.2. <hi>I counſel thee to keep the Kings commandment, and that in regard of the oath of God.</hi> Where this comes, the Oath and Covenant is indiſſolubly binding. If we once <hi>lift up our hand to the moſt high God,</hi> he will be ſure to lift up his hand againſt us, if we <hi>Vow,</hi> and <hi>not pay;</hi> be we few, or many.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor will the impoſing, or not impoſing of it by Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority alter the Caſe. For, it is obſervable, that in all ſuch Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Vows and Covenants, neither the <hi>Supreme</hi> Magiſtrates <hi>impoſition,</hi> or ſo much as conſent, is at all recorded in Scripture, or mentioned; which ſhews that there is no neceſſity of either. It is <hi>God,</hi> not <hi>Kings,</hi> that makes the Covenant obligatory. Take an inſtance or two.</p>
               <p>The one is of <hi>all Iſrael,</hi> in the Wilderneſs. When they were ſet upon by <hi>King Arad the Canaanite,</hi> who (at firſt worſted them) <hi>and took ſome of them priſoners; Iſrael vowed a vow to the Lord, and ſaid, If thou wilt indeed deliver this people into my hand, then I will utterly deſtroy their Cities</hi>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Num 21.2</note>. Here is no word, or hint of <hi>Moſes</hi> (their <hi>Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,</hi> as this Doctor unadviſedly calls him:) yet the <hi>Vow and Covenant</hi> was binding. For God took notice of it, and by his acting confirmed it. <hi>The Lord hearkened to the voice of Iſrael, and delivered up the Canaanites, and they utterly deſtroyed them, and their Cities</hi> ver. 3.</p>
               <p>The other is of <hi>Judah,</hi> and part of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (many hundred years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) in the days of <hi>Aſa;</hi> who being by him <hi>gathered together at Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> to make an offering to the Lord, <hi>they entred into a Covenant to ſeek the Lord God of their fathers, with all their heart, and with all their ſoul, That whoſoever would not ſeek the Lord God of Iſrael, ſhould be put to death, whether ſmall or great, whether man or woman; and they ſwore unto the Lord with a loud voice.—And all Judah rejoyced at the oath,—and be was found of them, and the Lord gave them reſt round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout,</hi> 2 Chron. 15.12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here was a National Covenant, and a Divine acceptance of it. Yet no word, or ſyllable of <hi>Aſa,</hi> as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152539:14"/>
                  <hi>impoſing,</hi> or <hi>confirming</hi> of it. Which is evidence enough, that the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing,</hi> or <hi>conſenting</hi> of a King, is not of the eſſence of a Legitimate Covenant: It is enough that God owns it, and commands perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance. Nor can any one inſtance be given, throughout the whole Book of God, that any <hi>Oath, Vow,</hi> or <hi>Covenant,</hi> to which the King, or Supreme Magiſtrate, would not, or did nor <hi>conſent,</hi> was upon that reaſon or groud made null and void: or, that any King ever went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to vacate, and adnul any Covenant made with God without the <hi>conſent</hi> of the <hi>King.</hi> It is then no other but blaſpheming the <hi>Gods,</hi> to term the late Parliament <hi>bungling Reformers,</hi> for <hi>doing Church-work without the Maſter-builders, Kings and Biſhops;</hi> if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to the <hi>Covenant.</hi> If he doth not ſo, then this is but a piece of railing <hi>Non-ſenſe,</hi> pull'd in by head and ears, to vent his gaul upon his betters.</p>
               <p>Do not all Parliaments adviſe and conſult with whom they think meet, even in matters of Religion and Eccleſiaſtical affairs as well as Civil, and Vote and paſs them before they offer them to the King? did they not ſo, in this? And did not his then Majeſty take them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſideration, and condeſcend to ſo much, as they gave him time to conſider of? without declaring againſt the reſt, but only ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>conſent,</hi> till his Conſcience might be better ſatisfied?</p>
               <p>Nay, even that which was never offered to his Majeſty at all, (being no way contrary or contradictory to the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi>) was never oppoſed, or contradicted by him. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 5. 1641. taken by both Houſes of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: and afterwards, by the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> alone, impoſed on all the Kingdom, without ſo much as asking his Majeſties <hi>conſent:</hi> which was never controuled, or diſallowed by the King, albeit he was then in Perſon reſiding at <hi>White-hall,</hi> and could not be ignorant of what was done therein.</p>
               <p>And, what ails the man to make ſuch a noiſe about the <hi>impoſing</hi> of the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> without the then King, who was then abſent! Did not both <hi>Ezra,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> alſo draw all the people into a ſolemn <hi>Covenant</hi> with God
<note n="t" place="margin">Ezra. 10.3 Neh. 9.38.</note>, without ſpecial Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (unleſs for reparing the <hi>Temple</hi>) from the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarch, then their Soveraign; albeit they were not free Subjects, but <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> and one of them the menial ſervant of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> then by Conqueſt Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour of <hi>Judah?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor did his late Majeſty ever command the renouncing of the ſaid <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> taken by both Kingdoms, <hi>Sept.</hi> 11. 1643. albeit he publiſhed a <hi>Proclamation, Jun.</hi> 21. in the 19th year of his Reign, <hi>viz. An.</hi> 1643. againſt that other <hi>Vow and Covenant,</hi> which was about that time, taken by the <hi>Lords and Commons,</hi> and by them appointed to be <hi>taken by every man in the Cities of</hi> London, Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152539:15"/>
                  <hi>and the Suburbs thereof, and throughout the whole Kingdom:</hi> the adminiſtring and taking of which (by ſuch as had not taken it) were by that Proclamation, for the reaſons therein contained, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</p>
               <p>But, albeit this were lately (by an enemy to the other Solemn League and Covenant) without warrant, reprinted, and ſcattered up and down as if it had been an interdicting and prohibiting thoſe that had taken it, to perform it; and to give ſome countenance to that railing Pamphlet of the Doctor here laid open in his colours; in hope that Ignorant ones would ſurely thereupon caſt off that Covenant of God: yet that was but a meer cheat and gullery, of which it behoves all honeſt men and ſober Chriſtians to take notice, and beware.</p>
               <p>Nor are Oaths and Covenants once ſolemnly taken, to be caſt off and diſclaimed upon any pretence whatſoever, be there never ſo many defects and failings in the impoſing or taking of them, unleſs the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of them be ſinful, as that of thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> that <hi>bound themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Oath of Execration,</hi> or <hi>curſe, not to eat or drink till they had killed Paul</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Act. 23.14</note>. This I have ſaid enough unto already; yet do repeat it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſince the writing of the premiſes, I have met with a Book inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance which have been laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide for many years,</hi> &amp;c. which tells us
<note n="w" place="margin">Pag. 5.</note>, That <hi>though there be many infirmities and miſcarriages committed in the making and taking of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Oaths; and although the things they oblige unto, be againſt the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the people; and though the breach and violation thereof, hath the countenance of fair and ſpecious intents and ends, ſeemingly conducing unto the publique good of the people; yet neither all nor any of theſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, doth either make void the obligations of thoſe Oaths, nor deliver the people from the great guilt of the ſin which is committed in the violation thereof, nor ſecure them from the dreadful judgement of God.</hi> Who is the Author hereof, I know not; but I am confident that the Doctor and he aim both at one mark: which makes me to alledge him.</p>
               <p>It is true, there is another Book lately reprinted, bearing this Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; <hi>Reaſons of the preſent Judgement of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of Oxford</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>the Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>approved by general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in a full Convocation,</hi> June 1. 1647. in which Book many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are alledged why thoſe who were then <hi>Maſters, Scholars, Officers, and other Members of that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> could not take that <hi>Covenant,</hi> and another <hi>Negative Oath.</hi> But that no way concerneth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Caſe, for their <hi>Reaſons</hi> tend only to <hi>their own juſtification</hi> for their <hi>not taking</hi> of the <hi>Covenant and Oath</hi> then tendred to them, not, to fall upon others who had already taken it. Therefore there is no need to add any Anſwers thereunto, although he that cauſed it to be <hi>reprinted,</hi> pretendeth to do it, <hi>for the ſatisfaction of others;</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in any ſenſe, reach thoſe who have taken the <hi>Covenant</hi> already.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:152539:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And now, good Mr. Doctor, think more ſeriouſly in cold blood, of your high preſumption, in caſting ſo much dirt upon that <hi>Covenant</hi> which his preſent gracious Majeſty hath ſo highly honoured; of which, perhaps, you may one day be required to render an account, if men have any zeal for his Majeſties honour. I forbear Particulars, in this: but you may do well to lay to heart particularly, what becomes you herein.</p>
               <p>Nor hath this Kingdom onely entered into a Solemn League and Covenant themſelves: but, they have approved, even in Parliament, what others have done in like caſes abroad. When the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> (even without their King) entred into a <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> among themſelves, (before their joyning with <hi>England</hi> in this) and were threatned to be chaſtiſed, for that, and other things, by a puiſſant Army; yet afterwards, upon a through debate thereof in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> it was declared by King and Parliament, That <hi>our Brethren of</hi> Scotland <hi>had done nothing but what became Loyal and obedient Subjects; and were thereupon, by Act of Parliament, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly righted in all the Churches of this Kingdom, where they had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea,
<note place="margin">See the <hi>Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Covenant, ordered by the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Feb.</hi> 9. 1643.</note> the ſame <hi>Exhortation</hi> (out of which the precedent Paragraph is extracted) telleth us, That neither this <hi>Doctrine</hi> nor <hi>Practiſe</hi> hath been (formerly) <hi>deemed ſeditious, or unwarrantable by the</hi> (former) <hi>Princes that have ſate upon the</hi> (Engliſh) <hi>Throne, but juſtified and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>of bleſſed memory, with the expence of much Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Noble Blood, in the united Provinces of the</hi> Netherlands, <hi>combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not onely without, but againſt the unjuſt violence of</hi> Philip (the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond) <hi>of</hi> Spain (firſt and chiefly in matters of Religion) <hi>King</hi> James (of like bleſſed memory) <hi>followed her ſteps, ſo far as to approve their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to enter into League with them</hi> as free States; <hi>which was after continued by his laſt Majeſty, who both by his Expedition for relief of</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel <hi>in</hi> France, <hi>and by his ſtrict confederacy</hi> (and Allyance) <hi>with the the late Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>notwithſtanding all the importunity of</hi> Spain <hi>to the contrary, did ſet to his ſeal, That all that had been done by his Royal Anceſtors, in maintenance of thoſe who had ſo engaged and combined themſelves, was juſt and warrantable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, Mr. Doctor, I have given you ſome <hi>patterns</hi> of Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Chriſtians, beſide the <hi>Holy League</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the two Houſes of Parliament (whom you take pleaſure, every where to beſpatter, as if they were Fools and Rebels) in <hi>England,</hi> and our Brethren in <hi>Scotland.</hi> I forbear to mention <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>Cantons,</hi> the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> and others, becauſe I have ſaid enough already to ſhew the fowlneſs of your Pen, and the falſhood of him that held it, in ſaying, there is <hi>no pattern</hi> of ſuch a Covenant in <hi>any ages of the Church, and that we never read nor heard of any</hi> Covenanting <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (until the Ligue Sainte in <hi>France</hi>)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152539:16"/>
                  <hi>except thoſe who in Baptiſm were ſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt, and ſo entred into that Covenant,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 11.</p>
               <p>I have now taken my walk through your gaudy Field: but have gathered little fruit. I therefore forbear further progreſs; unleſs to take a view of Her whom you call <hi>Your dear Mother the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, pag. 5. I pray, who, and what is She? Which Queſtion I ask not, as if I were of opinion that there is none ſuch: but, to know of you whom you take Her to be. I have read of one <hi>Mother of us all</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> I know no more <hi>Mothers,</hi> although I know more Churches. I have read in the <hi>Articles of Religion,</hi> eſtabliſhed in 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 12.
<note n="y" place="margin">Art. 19.</note> That <hi>the viſible Church of Chriſt is a Congregation of faithful men, in the which the pure Word of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, according to Chriſts Ordinance, in all thoſe things that of neceſſity are requiſite to the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, you are <hi>not ſo rude an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtander, nor ſo uncritical a Speaker. By the Church of</hi> England, <hi>you plainly and charitably mean that part of mankind in this</hi> Polity <hi>or</hi> Nation <hi>which having been called, baptiſed, and inſtructed, by lawful Miniſters in the Myſteries and Duties of the Goſpel, maketh a joynt and publick Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith, and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, in the name, and as the ſenſe of the whole Nation,</hi> &amp;c. Thus you, in your <hi>Tears, Sighs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of the Church of</hi> England, pag. 24. Then, all <hi>man-kind</hi> in this <hi>Polity</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> making ſuch a <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> is your <hi>Dear Mother.</hi> Are not you then, <hi>Terrae Filius,</hi> Sir? St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Hieruſalem which is above, is the Mother of us all.</hi> But you tell us, Your <hi>Mother</hi> is (not <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>England,</hi> which is below, and not <hi>free.</hi> Much joy may you have of her. I can own her as a <hi>Church,</hi> but not as a <hi>Mother.</hi> I have read of no <hi>Mothers</hi> in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, in relation to <hi>Churches,</hi> but onely <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> (not Earthly, but Coeleſtial:) and <hi>Babylon, the great Whore, the Mother of Harlots</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Rev. 17.1, 5.</note>. If the Doctor have found out a third, much good may ſhe do him. Now I ſee what makes him ſo excentrick and extravagant: namely, his ſucking too much of his <hi>Mothers Milk,</hi> when ſhe had eaten too much poyſonous meat of <hi>Arminianiſm, Socinianiſm,</hi> and <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, Sir, I ſhall for this time take my leave of you, with this cloſe: that whereas you (pag. 25.) vant, that, <hi>in two days you fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed thoſe Anſwers and Solutions;</hi> truly, Sir, I think ſo too: and do believe, that whoever ſhall carefully compare thoſe <hi>Anſwers</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions</hi> with this <hi>Reply,</hi> (which coſt more time) will be of the ſame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion: and, that the ſpirit of perverſneſs, pride, and time-ſerving ambition, did dictate them unto you.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152539:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>I <hi>Had almoſt forgotten your high Commendation of Dr.</hi> Uſhers <hi>Model of reformed Epiſcopacy, in his</hi> Reduction: <hi>which, for my part, I diſlike not. Only I muſt take occaſion hence to tell you; or rather others, that ſince the reprinting of that</hi> Reduction <hi>of</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy <hi>into the form of a</hi> Synodical Government <hi>(which little Piece was truly</hi> Dr. <hi>Uſhers child</hi>) <hi>there hath a Baſtard appear'd, which is called,</hi> The Biſhop of Armagh's Direction concerning the Liturgy, and Epiſcopal Government, <hi>ſaid to be written</hi> at the requeſt of the Houſe of Commons, <hi>in the year</hi> 1642. <hi>Which is a meer fiction, and a lye. For ſo Dr.</hi> Bernard <hi>in his Book inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled,</hi> The judgement of the Archbiſhop of Armagh, <hi>&amp;c. aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth us, pag.</hi> 160, <hi>That in</hi> An. 1640. <hi>There was a Book prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, intituled</hi> The Biſhop of Armaghs judgment to the Houſe of Parliament, concerning the Liturgy, and Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. <hi>And in</hi> An. 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>another Book intituled</hi> Vox Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernia, <hi>being ſome pretended Notes of his at a Publique Faſt. Both theſe at his Petition, were ſuppreſſed by</hi> Order from the Houſe of Lords and Commons, Feb. 11. 1641. <hi>And now revived, to thruſt out the other, which is his Legitimate iſſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
